welcome to entanglement radio on the
conversations from the brink Network I
am your host Angela Levesque and this
show is all about the potential and
possibilities of what it means to be
human
our guest today is an evolutionary
philosopher and systems designer Daniel
smocked inverter and we are going to be
talking all about obviously our human
potential but we're going to be talking
about blending science spirituality
philosophy how we create meaning in our
lives and talk about this idea of
emergence in synergy and a
self-organizing self-organizing universe
which are I think really important comes
concepts to understand and really
appreciate how we can implement those in
our lives so that we can make the
changes necessary coming up next week we
have Lisa Knox use the author of six
award-winning books of creative
nonfiction and we're going to talk about
the cultural and spiritual factors that
lead to women's bodies issues eating
disorders and ageism so I'm excited
about that if you'd like to know more
about myself or the show my website is
Angelo Levesque comm and you can find me
on Facebook and on Twitter at Hestia
health and you can also find out more
about this show entanglement radio and
my project conversations from the brink
which is all about talking about insight
and inspiration for humanity's next step
and that's conversations from the brink
calm so with that I want to introduce my
guest daniel has a transdisciplinary
science background with a whole system's
complexity and integral framework you
love solving seemingly intractable
problems by reassessing the foundational
data of axioms of the field and then
restructuring it from the ground up
Daniel was the academic dean for a
college of mind-body medicine and has
consulted from any cutting-edge
integrative doctors and medical clinics
to find help find novel solutions for
phlex cases he created and ran a
cutting-edge think-tank developing
complex system solutions for
environmental and social issues and has
directed a transdisciplinary group of
scholars on a philosophy of mind project
addressing core questions of mind brain
interface and developing a axiomatic
reformulation for the genealogy of
neuroscience wow that's a mouthful but
with that I feel very honored and
blessed to welcome Daniel to the program
hi Daniel how you doing I'm happy to be
here thanks for having me well I'm
excited you know as I'm connecting with
you and I'm reading about all of these
different projects that you do one of
the things that I find really
interesting with people who kind of have
been involved in over so many different
disciplines and fields of study is what
is it that drives you it's an
intersection of a number of things so
I'm probably like most people very moved
by suffering suffering of other sentient
beings humans and nonhumans and how to
reduce that eliminate the foundational
causes of it this is a core call for me
in life that is across all different
topics I'm also called by the positive
side of their experience so how do we
create world systems that make possible
and induce not only less suffering but
higher quality of life across all
meaningful aspects of what quality of
life is for all life now and ongoingly
and all the different facets that come
together to make that possible and also
just by a deep love of universe which
leads to a fascination and wanting to
learn all that all that I can which of
course ends up applying itself to the
previous topics but is a is a lure in
and of itself well I I think I want to
start with this idea so I was watching
this short talk that you gave and you
were talking about the
Neri universe story kind of the one that
we've been able to piece together now
which is much more whole and complex and
very different from kind of the way that
we look at things in science where we
like to get mechanistic and break things
down into parts that we can then analyze
and so I want you to give us a view of
the way that you see this this universal
story and tell us about what it means to
be self-organizing mm-hmm there's a lot
in there so to really have a proper
context for the scientific worldview in
the scientific process as we know it and
what we call reductionist thinking it's
important to kind of understand how it
emerged so when we look at Copernicus
Galileo Descartes Newton this was really
what helped to deliver us from the dark
ages where people had different
religious ideas about the nature of
absolute reality that were the basis of
Crusades and the burning of witches and
you know so many things that had no
empirical basis and empiricism being
able to say hey wait no matter what we
think it is we might not be able to
agree on God's name but we can agree on
the speed of sound you can agree on the
speed of light we can agree on whether
and solve problems we haven't been able
to solve a galileo finding the rate of
things falling and it seemed like not
only the ability to explain a tremendous
amount which it was and to empower us
with the application and technology
which it was but also a way to get
everybody on the same page because if
there is objective empirical reality
independent of our beliefs about it and
we can all kind of find that out as a
profound unification of that so it's
important to understand how crucial that
is and also why it you know emerge with
the philosophical kind of fervor that I
had of a movement away from subjective
based belief systems towards object
based belief system
now of course then the problem ended up
becoming in the huge success of that
that when we define what is real by
what's measurable what's objective what
is available to empiricism then we end
up defining that which is subjective as
not real just by definition right that
becomes part of that axiom and so then
consciousness and our whole inferiority
is not real right it's first-person
stuff and science is the domain of
third-person stuff and as scientists
continue to be able to explain so many
things that we had previously had in
spiritual philosophic religious
categories been able to explain them
better in many ways this has led to the
whole technological advancement of
humanity which is you know beautiful and
the downside of it of course is it has
no interior t so either consciousness
consciousness is not real at all or it's
the somehow emergent property of brains
and neural networks that usually leads
to interpretations of having no agency
meaning etc and so as we take some of
the next steps in our understanding of
the universe beyond some of the early
religious concepts and beyond the
earlier scientific concepts to basically
just progressively better and better and
more nuanced and more interconnected
understandings of the nature of reality
wherein we start to look at with it even
within the third-person even within what
science looks at in very complex systems
like biologic systems there are so many
variables interacting so dynamically
that to try and understand those systems
by just looking at individual parts
which seem to make a lot of sense for us
right like when you think about in the
time of early science that we could
calculate a ballistic curve that we've
done the pendulum dowsing before now we
could use Newtonian mechanics in
calculus to plot that curve perfectly
because there were only two variables we
had to affect right which is that the
angle of the Cannonball and how much
gunpowder we put in we could take what
seems like a difficult scenario and
reduce it to a small
number of variables and have a
tremendous amount of insight and impact
but in certain kind of complex systems
where the variables actually do
different things in relationship with
other variables than they do on their
own and where they can't where they
interact so quickly and complexly
reductionism has limits of how
explanatory and how useful it can be and
so we've had an emerging field of system
science how do we understand whole self
interacting systems and one of the key
insights here is that when we take the
parts apart like say we take a cell we
take it apart and we look at each
individual type of molecular structure
we look at the organelles we look at the
organic molecules that make it up
none of those organelles none of those
molecules on their own breathe and yet
the cell as a whole breathes and so we
say what part breeze and none of them do
right well it is the complex orderly
relationship of all those parts in that
way that leads to respiration and life
as a whole as an emergent property and
for this property of synergy which is
the behavior of a whole system that's
not found in the parts taken separately
is something where reductionism isn't
able to give us the whole picture
understand the parts that's important
it's just not the whole thing
understanding how the parts come
together and what the relationships are
that aren't found in the parts
separately what the whole is there's
also a big part of the picture so this
is where kind of the fields of system
science and complexity science have
emerged and given us better insights
even into the nature of third-person
physical reality and then we also have
this movement to look at what if
consciousness first-person experience
isn't well explained exclusively as an
emergent property of physical systems
right brain etc and even even if it was
if I'm looking at the EEG of a buddhist
monk who's in some deep meditative state
i can explain their aging patterns but i
have no idea what their experience is
like or how to get there and so there is
a need for a process of understanding
the texture and the nature of
subjectivity of consciousness the first
person to be
third person completely so science is
going through or are our philosophic
system that sciences apartment is going
through an evolution to include more
complex understanding of the nature of
third person and a deeper understanding
of the nature of first person and how
those come together well that was very
well explained
so as I'm listening to you say this and
many people in in my community and so I
have a largely spiritually based
community and we like to cherry-pick
science to validate our spiritual
beliefs which I kind of find annoying
but anyway what I understand what you
were saying but why do we need to
quantify and categorize and and
understand subjective experience why can
it not just be something that runs maybe
parallel or why do they I don't think I
even a why do we need to have an
explanation for that experience why
can't the experience be part of the
package of the whole does that make
sense
I will speak to what I think makes sense
okay couple things say you take a system
like Buddhism where there are certain
kinds of processes that are for rather
than exploring this nature physical
reality right the speed of sound or the
pH of a of a fluid they're exploring
aspects of one's own conscious
experience so do this kind of breathing
pay attention to these kinds of things
move your attention in these ways and
then notice what you experience and this
is both because if many people do that
and they find some similar things
independent of being pre suggested to
look for certain things then not just
we're not just exploring subjectivity
we're getting through this inter
subjective exploration of what might be
about consciousness about experience as
a whole that informs all of us and we
just become better at navigating our own
internal landscape right so this is
relevant if we want to be able to move
out of anxiety and depression and etc
into states of subjective experience
that are more fun to be in and more
creative and make our availability to
others better and so it's it's not
simply to like prove something it's
actually learned the contours of the
dimension of the universe the subjective
dimension so that we can navigate it
better and understand it better and
understand because it's fascinating but
also understand so that we can navigate
and help others to I would also say that
why it's relevant to really understand
the relationship between consciousness
and physics between mind and brain body
is one we live in a system in a world
right now where science has had so much
explanatory power and you know has been
able to make the radically complex
technology that's allowing you and I to
talk wirelessly across the world right
now and then for this to be heard by all
your listeners and and have us exploring
Mars and deep reach to the brain I like
this because of its explanatory power it
has become the dominant philosophical
system and if it's a philosophic system
that ultimately in most interpretations
says what's real is physical stuff maybe
this is called physicalism physical
particles are real and consciousness
either doesn't exist at all review
called radical luminous abysm or it
exists but it actually couldn't have
agency right it arises as the submergent
property from the brain and therefore it
can witness only but have no causal
influence which is an inexorable Eenie
list right meaningless views that's a
real bummer and it's not just a real
bummer it's a real problematic thing for
science being perceived as uncommon sir
a table with ethics right because ethics
involves the experience of sentient
creatures and science
you know that's not its domain and so we
have this technological force its
science as a system of seeing the world
that gives rise to technology that gives
rise to the way we're building and
affecting the world that effect
subjective experience but without any
compass or guidance system because it
doesn't commensurate with ethics so it's
very important to actually have a deep
scientific exploration of the nature of
consciousness so that we can actually
affect and direct the development of
technology right in the development of
our built world and I don't think that
I'm disagreeing with you I think that
that's an important piece but I also
find that the experience aspect the not
because I feel and this is actually
something that I have been working
through and in my world we talk about
the masculine and feminine energies and
I tend to be very like I spend a lot of
time in my mind I spend a lot of time in
deep contemplation thinking about the
things and one of the things that I have
been exploring is this idea of
embodiment and instead of thinking about
what it is that I'm doing being in the
experience which to me is slightly
different it's not a it's not about
better or worse it's not a value
judgment that this is the correct way
this is the wrong way but there is
something different about having the
awareness from an intellectual
perspective and embodying the experience
and I think that that's where you know I
do a lot of work with cancer survivors
and we they get a lot of people telling
them a lot of the research and this is
what needs to do but one of the reasons
they told me they really like to come to
my classes because I create we create
meaning from from data we create meaning
from story and experience and being not
just like the other day we talked about
Candice Curt and she wrote a book called
the molecules of emotion which are all
about you know neuropeptides and the the
connections between like the bio
biochemical correlates of emotion
basically and then we went and we had
the
into meditation and connected very
metaphorically energetically spiritually
with our emotional bodies and so there
was this play between understanding you
know
dr. pert and her amazing research and
then we had the experience of the
embodiment of that emotion in itself and
so that's where I kind of where I'm
looking at your stuff and it's just
incredibly fascinating and I love it but
it's so intellectual and I just I also
interview a lot of people that talk
about you know the heart and I I know we
can obviously talk very biologically
about the heart but talk about the heart
more metaphorically or spiritually where
do you feel that that fits in to this
idea of emergence and this
self-organizing universe I gave you a
lot there again didn't it that's great
we create false dichotomies that lead to
either
unnecessarily polarized partial views or
kind of pendulum swinging back and forth
between partial truths we need to learn
how to transcend the false dichotomy so
for instance embodiment and experience
versus intellect and understanding or
heart versus mind there's no versus
right it's how do we evolve and expand
both and the relationship for the full
human experience and so let's say let's
say we talk about any kind of very deep
transpersonal numinous spiritual
experience so let's say we talk about a
Vision Quest or a medicine journey okay
so say we take a medicine journey and
someone has an experience right they're
having a very real deep profound maybe
you know life-altering experience then
they come out of it and they're going to
interpret that through a cognitive model
and so say someone goes into a journey
and part of what happened there was a
dark part of the journey and they saw
monsters chasing them which is it this
is not an uncommon thing and they come
out and there's a particular
a worldview that says well the medicine
was letting you see into the astral
realm and there are monsters and asked
for a realm that are actually after you
because whatever you did bad things in
the past life or that's just where they
are and so now you need to put crystals
around yourself and into the person
having more fear more disempowerment etc
or someone else has the exact same
experience and they have a different
kind of worldview facilitation that says
maybe the monsters were the way that
your mind brain complex symbolically
represented unresolved fears and
emotions maybe you know represents
issues you had with your parents or
whatever in childhood let's try again
and now and then the person faces the
monster and then the monster becomes
their dad and then they make peace with
their dad and then it becomes their
dad's and a child and that this whole
healing model actually ends up affecting
the meaning you make ends up affecting
how that experience is stored how its
interpreted and how it becomes a part of
your behavioral and experiential basis
for the rest of your life so if I only
did the cognitive side and talked to
people about like we're talking now the
worldview of psychedelics and no one
ever had an experience with it for
instance or meditation or whatever they
we also wouldn't get there so it really
is at the synergy of people's experience
and working with technologies and
processes like meditation like breath
work like transpersonal psychology like
psychedelics like whatever working with
technologies and processes that are
deeply experiencial deeply embodied and
also being able to go into those as best
pre framed as possible because of what
we've learned from previous peoples
experience and interpret them as best as
possible within our cognate model so in
what I would call a full human
experience someone's thinking and their
intuiting would actually align and they
would continue to work on developing and
advancing both of them as necessary
parts of a full human experience mm-hmm
right on I I'm like I'm definitely in
your
why on that I love that so let's you
talk about this idea use the word
emergence neither sorts energy and is
looking through your website so that
often right now we are having emergence
through emergency and I I just love that
idea cuz I've always kind of referred to
it as the band-aid approach that we see
something that pops up and then we find
the easiest solution the path of least
resistance to deal with that one little
thing without looking at you know the
systemic issues underneath so I was
hoping that you could talk about this
idea of emergence through emergency and
how individuals can can help shift us
out of that I guess mode of dealing with
things yeah so this was a term first
coined as far as I'm aware by
Buckminster Fuller and really talked
about it as a sociological even just a
deeper universal process where sometimes
emergency I mean this is the same as
necessity as the mother of invention and
so many concepts like this but where an
emergency motivates a foundational level
shift that wouldn't have been motivated
previously or wasn't being motivated
previously and so of course we can have
a situation where a problem arises and
we just deal with it reactively post
facto in a band-aid way and we see that
all over the place and it's it might be
necessary but it's inadequate before we
really care about there other times
where an emergency is big enough that
rather than just put a bandaid on it and
then move back to life as it was it
actually requires some core
restructuring at a personal level of our
life or at a collective level of how we
organize right as a as a species or
technologically or we we have so many
scenarios were like as we were getting
into World War one which was represented
this level of war an existential threat
we hadn't had we ended up developing
some new technologies that became the
basis of how the world became
interconnected transportation and
community
technologies as we're getting into World
War two we mined more copper in the
first year the u.s. joined World War two
than we had in the whole previous
history of humanity which then ended up
leading to the electrification of the
world and then the interconnected
communication of the world Cold War
giving rise that's becoming you know in
interplanetary species so but we you can
see that we continued with the warning
direction so there's a deeper set of
shifts ahead for us but probably so many
people who are listening and part of
your community of experience that
whether it was a cancer diagnosis or
whether it was a midlife crisis or
family member dying that there was some
personal kinds of emergency that shook
up the whole way of being that they had
had that forced like a revaluation of
who they are why they are how they are
that then led to a fundamentally new
path it was more aligned with their
purpose and so that happens right and
when we look at all of the major issues
facing the world today environmentally
socially on so many levels we have
emergency right we have collective
emergency that is you potentially
existential and band-aids solutions
aren't big enough and these solutions
will not fix ocean acidification or
biodiversity loss or so many of those
level catastrophic and existential
issues that the only thing that will fix
them our foundational shifts at a
species wide level and how we orient in
universe and one of the key things is to
get that emergence through emergency is
kind of like it's kind of like the
safety that if we have not consciously
proactively evolved in necessary ways
into the waves that we have been
behaving have led to problems then
hopefully those problems are our you
know a wake-up call a smack to then
change but we don't have to be bound to
that being the primary way we evolve
forever as soon as as soon as we stop
identifying primarily as nouns and we
started identifying as verbs we start
identifying as dynamic become
in processes of evolving and blossoming
then as when we identified that there's
this evolutionary process that creates
more complexity that has brought about
biology and mammals and us and that with
that more orderly complexity comes new
emergent properties and capabilities we
can actually kind of identify as not
only the result of evolutionary process
but in a meaningful way that that the
evolutionary process brought us about as
a species with abstraction that can then
contemplate evolution so that the
evolutionary process woke up to itself
in us where we can now think about the
future understand how evolution as a set
of processes is increasing elegant order
of complexity and we can participate
with evolution we can not just kind of
be a part of the whole unconsciously
governed by genetic programs but we can
become agents for the whole itself and
you know what barban Mark's Edwards
calls conscious evolution comes to
participate with it and once we identify
as evolutionary's we don't need pushed
by emergency or catastrophe or pain to
evolve because we are not sitting here
as like complacent things we are
dynamically being drawn by what Tara to
start on called the lure of becoming
right by the continuous process of
creating a more beautiful world not
because things aren't good enough now
not because we're dissatisfied but
because it's the nature of universe to
be evolving and becoming us our nature
to do that and as soon as we start
really shifting into that space of
active becoming we D necessitate
emergency and pain as evolutionary
drivers yes you and I have very
different tools in our tool bags but I
think they're both of us that I mean
that is ultimately when I work with
people I I want to help them get excited
about life so they're not doing things
because somebody says they should or
their doctor says or theirs because of
exactly what you're saying and as I was
listening to that talk that was up on
Facebook that's what I could feel that
sense of passion that sense of wanting
to move towards something in real
that we are these dynamic these
ever-changing dynamic beings and what
happens when we decide to do that
consciously versus you know just letting
our environment or whatever the media
just shift us so if I'm listening to you
and I love it I'm getting excited and I
can feel your passion are there are a
few things that need to shift within us
culturally or in our society like her
there are a few Lynch pins that we could
pull that would give people a greater
access or an understanding of our
potential yes and they are at micro and
macro levels macro levels so when we
said earlier that there are these false
dichotomies one classic false dichotomy
is kind of we can see represented right
now in political process in the
difference between what has been thought
of as the primary philosophic elements
of the democratic or republican platform
it's also kind of mirrored in the
communist and capitalist platforms which
can be oversimplified as the the primary
kind of truth of the Republican platform
is this agency oriented perspective hey
I pulled myself up by my bootstraps even
though I came through from a difficult
situation we want other people who are
responsible self directing agents pull
themselves up by their bootstraps we
don't want social services that make
people lazy independent and etc and we
want to maximize for for agency right
and the collective is the result of all
of the individual human behavior so if
we you know this isn't what capitalism
would say similarly if we maximize
individual freedom and individual
incentive we'll have the best collective
possible because the Collector's made it
by individuals so that's that side of
the story then the other side of the
story which in various ways both the
Democratic and I'm not saying that any
current candidates represent these well
but the Democratic platform and in a
bigger way the Communist platform is
hell
hey but wait the individuals are
actually being conditioned by the
environments that they are born into and
raised in and that we see very clear
statistical correlations between if
someone is born in poverty grows up in
situations with low education what they
are likely to achieve experience their
statistical likelihood for crime for etc
and even though there are a few cases
where someone pulled themselves up by
their bootstraps there's statistical
outliers so since the individuals are
conditioned by their environment
let's make better environments
collective environments that support all
individuals to do better and so then the
question is well do we want better
environments the conditioned individuals
better or do we want better individuals
that help create better collectives and
environments and answer is obviously yes
both and that these are mutually
symbiotic and they again the idea that
there's something they caught them is
here just means we haven't understood
the scenario well enough can we see if
we offer a model for increased agency of
the individual likes a libertarian model
right like the capitalist model but it
doesn't factor for how that individuals
agency ends up affecting others or the
whole well enough
then we end up leading to a situation of
what we you know so much what we see in
the world right pathologic destructive
competition hoarding of resources
requiring more resources being extracted
from the earth for Less actual abundance
you know continuing enmity etc and the
tragedy of the Commons similarly though
if we try to optimize for the collective
in a way that squishes the agency of the
individual then we end up getting
dissent and neither the breakdown of
those systems like has happened with
communist attempts or the enforcement of
those systems authoritarian Li which
neither of those are good so the
question is how do we optimize for
people's own agentic desire to evolve
and Express and self actualize and their
communal desire to be part of larger
holes and contribute to and take care of
them and the truth is if let's say we
look at a human body
the liver isn't trying to get ahead at
the expense of the kidneys and vice
versa in fact they all need each other
because it's a it's a very closely
interconnected system and so they all
work very symbiotically when we realize
that our planet is this tiny little
fragile organic spaceship in this vast
cosmic so far to us uninhabitable space
and we are all on that spaceship
together and and there's really no room
for infighting right there's really no
room for there's no place called a way
that we can put our trash there's nobody
called others that we can advance
ourselves at the expense of when we get
how profoundly interconnected we are our
own best self actualisation and the best
support of the whole will actually be
identical if we factor all the cause and
effect loops so we need to really get
that at the level of our own
consciousness our own worldview and at
the level of our macroeconomic systems
and our infrastructure so imagine if we
had a macroeconomic system where it
wasn't that I could confer a lot of
material advantage by cutting down trees
and killing whales because as soon as I
kill that whale it's a million dollars
worth of well meat on my on my fishing
boat we're leaving it alive it's worth
nothing because the balance sheet of the
Commons isn't counted right that
economic model leads to massive
biodiversity loss ocean acidification
all the problems that we see imagine if
we had an economic system where the
incentive of every individual was
perfectly aligned with the well-being of
every other individual and of the
Commons and so people could take
incentive could move forward but the
collective is being advanced and move
forward and everyone's individual access
to all of the collective common wealth
is also growing so that's an example of
the macro shifts that they need to make
and at a micro level making sure that
our own worldview is we notice where we
start to have fall into thinking that we
can advantage ourself at the expense of
someone else or advantage other people
by sacrificing ourselves and get that
get over the false dichotomy and look
at how we can become more Omni
considerate more Omni positive through
better strategy well we only have a few
minutes left in so I think feel that
this segues nicely into your the newest
thing you're working on which is neuro
hacker and I find this very fascinating
somebody who does a lot of work in
mind-body stuff tell my listeners a
little bit about what neuro hacker is
and and why you felt it to be necessary
at this time mm-hmm
so when we're looking at how to bring
about better global civilization and not
through imposition but a self evolving
self-governing emergent global
civilization then we look at what are
all of the things that end up
influencing human experience and human
behavior and what are all the things
that lead to poor human experience
unnecessary kinds of suffering and that
lead to poor human behavior unnecessary
suffering induced in others via our
behavior and what leads to the opposite
of those and what can we do to maximally
influence move in the right direction
and again this is not control this is
recognizing we're being a we're being
conditioned by our environment all the
time anyways how can we be more
thoughtful about that to do a better job
with it and when we look at all the
categories of things that influence
human experience and human behavior we
see that there's there's ways that the
physical environment and world around us
does right the infrastructure itself and
the built world doesn't so the whole
field of environmental psychology
there's a lot and how do we rebuild the
physical world to both be not only
better for the planet and but to
affecting condition the humans within it
better and by condition I mean if you
have a world where to get energy you the
energy came through cold and you have
really have no options other than that
available to you and to not have access
to energy ends up leading to just you
know no no capability to do the things
you want to in the system then
you have to end up rationalizing
participating with something that you
know is causing inexorable suffering
somewhere else so infrastructure itself
conditions a certain aspect of empathy
out of everyone right the way that we
currently do it if we had a renewable
infrastructure it could condition
totally different things and people so
infrastructure is an area that affects
human experience and behavior our social
systems economics governance law
language all those other things we work
with there our worldview does our
definition of success or definition of
self other meaning right which we've
been talking about bar biology also does
and when we look at things like anxiety
or depression or brain fog or
meaninglessness there are contributors
to those in all of these categories but
specifically at the level of individuals
there's obviously psychologic trauma
ideas beliefs that we can deal with
through psychotherapy through personal
development methodologies that are
important that address what we could
kind of think of as the software side
but there is also Hardware
predispositions when we when we look at
any particular kind of neuropsychiatric
issue we can see a number of neuro
chemical neuro endocrine got brain
access and there are structural
correlates and actually identified some
of those correlates as causal to some of
those structures and so some of that can
be effected through mind brain interface
right things that you looked at we're
shifting mental pattern shifts physical
patterns but it goes both ways shifting
physical patterns and everyone who
started sleeping better and exercising
more and eating better had an experience
of shifting physiology in ways that
affect their moods how much kindness is
available to them everyone who's felt
really sick or had hormones that are
balances felt the opposite and so we
created no hunger collective to work on
understanding how to balance and
optimize the human physiology the
neurology and the Associated physiology
to support more optimized human
experience and human capability so this
is everything from increasing cognitive
capability
memory focus intelligence complex
thinking to increasing empathy
increasing the kind of neurologic
pathways that meditative non-symbolic
experience is mediated across and so we
have one technology that if you go to
the website and row hacker.com you'll
see is currently available we have many
many more in process our goal is to
actually have all that is meaningful in
the space of neuro technology vetted
curated synthesized and then
personalized so that the very best tools
for working on whatever it is that one
is wanting to work on are available to
them and that there's there is specific
guidance capable so that's what we're
working towards with that project so
fascinating when I was looking over the
website and would you describe it as a
nutraceutical so the products that you
have that have been specially formulated
to do like you said the cognitive
enhancements those just that looks
incredibly fascinating to me and I'm
very excited to try the product that you
see on the website now is called qualia
and it is a it is a nutraceutical it is
a nootropic which means cognitive
enhancing supplement we are not limited
to nutraceuticals we're working on
technology and the transcranial
stimulation space and EG neurofeedback
and basically all technology areas that
we believe to be fundamentally up
regulating of human capacity without any
kind of meaningful side-effects that's
our criteria but we started in
nutraceuticals and started in cognitive
enhancement for a number of reasons it's
an area that can produce it a tremendous
amount of positive shift for lots of
people and that is more familiar right
taking a pill is is an easier step for
many people than getting into devices
for trying to create a simulation that
are more foreign to it if as you
continue to stay tuned you'll see more
and more different kinds of technologies
becoming available but the first product
quality our goal was especially seeing
how much demand for productivity the
world has
and how much distraction and kind of
damage to people's focus and attention
there is and how much the world has
turned to you know Red Bull and energy
drinks and off-label you know adderall
as a smart drug and you know so many
things like that we wanted to see if we
could meet the needs that people are
trying to meet with that in terms of
increased creative productive flow
capabilities without the negative side
effects and even with lasting positive
benefits where we're rather than
overriding someone's regulatory system
we're working on supporting the
robustness of the regulatory system so
that instead of creating dependence we
actually create lasting positive effects
after someone stopped using this that
was our goal and we've been you know
we're continuing research and
development but we are very happy with
what we've been able to effect in people
so far yes well I'm very interested and
I will definitely be seeing what's next
because I just obviously this show I
started this show to talk about human
potential and I believe that there's
many arenas where human potential can be
accessed and activated within each other
and it I do I do think that there is
this this definitely the space for this
blending of technology in our biological
you know creating an interface between
that I also think that there's also
space for you know straight-up
meditation and and psychedelics I've
I've done quite a bit of that as well
but um I just want to thank you so much
so at this point in the show I just want
to leave you the opportunity to share
with people how they can find your
website shows social media anything
you'd like to leave my listeners with it
this time
yeah just a last thought on one other
dichotomy I'd love for people to see if
they're asked is the idea that nature
and Technology are somehow opposed they
have been because we have developed
technology without really understanding
how nature works without understanding
self-organization and complexity well
which has led to externalities but
that's not in
the technology nature evolved us and
evolved our capacity to evolve things
which our tools are extensions of the
evolutionary process of the future is
going to be both a very nature
integrated and very high-tech world
where our technology is an expression of
the natural world with the
self-organization and design complexity
of the natural world and so whether we
are meditating or whether we're using a
tropics I don't see those as
fundamentally different kinds of things
I see those as methodologies processes
technologies of understanding how to
navigate the human experience better
utilizing all that's available to us so
just a just a closing thought people can
see more of what we're doing with neuro
hacker Admiral hacker comments people
want to you know just see kind of what
I'm up to following me on Facebook is an
easy way well then oh I want to thank
you so much for being on the show today
you gave me a lot to think about
and yeah I would love to have you on
anytime and if you need any tests of
subjects for a year well coming up next
week we have loosen up and she's the
author of six award-winning books on and
we'll be talking about the cultural and
spiritual factors that lead to women's
bodies issues eating disorders and
ageism if you want to know more about
myself Angelou back you can go to Angela
over comm and if you want to know more
about our project here at conversations
from the brink we're more about
entertainment radio you can go to
conversations from the brink comm last
our show for you today thank you so much
for tuning in and we'll be back next
week
you